<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>devops on Gaveen Prabhasara</title>
    <link>https://gaveen.me/tags/devops/</link>
    <description>Recent content in devops on Gaveen Prabhasara</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Gaveen Prabhasara</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2020 20:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://gaveen.me/tags/devops/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>My Vim Story</title>
      <link>https://gaveen.me/2020/02/my-vim-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2020 20:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gaveen.me/2020/02/my-vim-story/</guid>
      <description>Once you have used &amp;lsquo;notepad.exe&amp;rsquo;, you have used all text editors—they said. A text editor is a text editor is a text editor—they said. After the first few years of running Linux/Unix professionally, I kind of subconsciously agreed with this idea, eventhough I knew Vim—I thought I knew Vim. But when other people who actually knew how to use Vim used it, Vim still looked like magic.
If you have worked in a command line at some point, I am sure you can appreciate the wisdom of learning how to use a text editing program properly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I don&#39;t believe in Kubernetes</title>
      <link>https://gaveen.me/2019/12/i-don-t-believe-in-kubernetes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Dec 2019 06:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gaveen.me/2019/12/i-don-t-believe-in-kubernetes/</guid>
      <description>I have always been a believer in Cloud Computing. Even when big executives of the world were calling it a fad, I believed in the cloud—or its promise. It was not so much an achievement to be had—rather as with to so many other people in tech—it spoke to me from a place of understanding. We may not have called it &amp;ldquo;cloud&amp;rdquo;, but when Amazon opened the gates of their Web Services to everyone, we saw good things we recognized with and we realized it was an opportunity to build things better.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The future of networking is software</title>
      <link>https://gaveen.me/2019/10/the-future-of-networking-is-software/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2019 06:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gaveen.me/2019/10/the-future-of-networking-is-software/</guid>
      <description>I believe the future of networking is software. To be a little more specific on my thoughts, I believe the future of networking in the data center is software-based. Water is wet, and on that note, thank you for coming to my TED talk. And, quick PS: clouds are also hosted in data centers.
While what I just mentioned maybe obvious to say—given how pretty much everything has its future in software—you would be surprised at the state of the networking industry if you came to it as an outsider.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>