<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Personal on Gaveen Prabhasara</title>
    <link>https://gaveen.me/categories/personal/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Personal on Gaveen Prabhasara</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>Gaveen Prabhasara</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2020 20:00:00 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://gaveen.me/categories/personal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>My Vim Story</title>
      <link>https://gaveen.me/2020/02/my-vim-story/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Feb 2020 20:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gaveen.me/2020/02/my-vim-story/</guid>
      <description>Once you have used &amp;lsquo;notepad.exe&amp;rsquo;, you have used all text editors—they said. A text editor is a text editor is a text editor—they said. After the first few years of running Linux/Unix professionally, I kind of subconsciously agreed with this idea, eventhough I knew Vim—I thought I knew Vim. But when other people who actually knew how to use Vim used it, Vim still looked like magic.
If you have worked in a command line at some point, I am sure you can appreciate the wisdom of learning how to use a text editing program properly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fictional/Anticipated Questions (FAQ)</title>
      <link>https://gaveen.me/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 06:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gaveen.me/about/</guid>
      <description>Obviously, not many people contact me asking things about this blog. So, I&amp;rsquo;m placing these fabricated questions here to tell you a little more about a few things.
 Are there more navigation options? Yes. Currently, site content is organized into main categories while each post may have tags.
 Categories Tags   Can I subscribe only to a section of this blog? Yes. Each of the categories and tags will have its own feed.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I thought I knew</title>
      <link>https://gaveen.me/2019/04/i-thought-i-knew/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2019 06:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gaveen.me/2019/04/i-thought-i-knew/</guid>
      <description>I thought I knew how being a father would be. I have a father, a good one. I understood that much. I have nephews and nieces, and I love them to bits. I understood that much. So when we become pregnant, I thought I had a pretty strong grip on how being a parent felt.
I knew I wasn&amp;rsquo;t nearly ready as I wanted to be, but I didn&amp;rsquo;t think I had a big gap of understanding on how a father felt about their child.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Whatever happened to that book?</title>
      <link>https://gaveen.me/2019/04/whatever-happened-to-that-book/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Apr 2019 06:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gaveen.me/2019/04/whatever-happened-to-that-book/</guid>
      <description>Today is the Sinhala (and Tamil) New Year day. As I sit in front of the computer to partake in my trade—as one does according to tradition—I want to try an answer a certain question.
Whatever happened to that book you were writing?—is not a question I have been asked too many times. You see, I am not a well-known writer at all—but I digress. I have in fact, been working for a while on at least two, maybe two and a half books—none of which are actually ready yet.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is the meaning of that poem?</title>
      <link>https://gaveen.me/2019/01/what-is-the-meaning-of-that-poem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2019 06:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gaveen.me/2019/01/what-is-the-meaning-of-that-poem/</guid>
      <description>I am a poet, and that much I can say without the uncertainty I allude in the current bio section of this blog which reads &amp;ldquo;SysAdmin, Programming Language Tourist, and Petty Dabbler of the Written Word&amp;rdquo;, or my first post here.
My work as a poet, or a writer is mainly to write. But, I write mainly for the sheer joy of reading it back, in every way I get to.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Here we go</title>
      <link>https://gaveen.me/2019/01/here-we-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 06:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gaveen.me/2019/01/here-we-go/</guid>
      <description>Where should I begin? Is this on?
Hello there! Welcome, fellow human being, and of course, any other that is reading. This is presumably Gaveen, and—despite all my efforts—you have found my blog. If this is the choice of Steins;Gate, who am I to complain.
There are no grand introductions here, nor any road maps to unveil—just the simple realization to be had that I may have moved my blog yet another time.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>